Edwin Markham Collection
Edwin Markham Collection
1914-1942
Markham, Edwin, 1852-1940.
6 folders (SC)
Correspondence, manuscripts, miscellany of the American poet and author.
2639547
Biographical History
Edwin Markham (1852-1940) was an American author and poet. Born and raised in California, he taught literature there until 1879 when he became Superintendent of Education for El Dorado County. Five California schools are named for him. In 1901 he relocated to Staten Island in New York, where he established the Poetry Society of America in 1910. In addition to his teaching, he wrote poetry and essays and lectured in numerous venues.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Edwin Markham Collection consists of correspondence, manuscripts, and a small amount of miscellany.
Correspondence contains four letters, two outgoing and two incoming. In one, writing to John Elfreth Watkins, he says of his mother that she "held her ground alone...as the head of a family for thirty years," and that "...the first and only play she ever took me to from our mountain home was Ten Nights in a Bar Room. None of her boys ever took to strong drink."
Manuscripts contains manuscripts for two essays and a poem, as well as one stanza of his well-known poem "Outwitted."
Miscellany consists of a broadside, a cancelled check, and a few clippings.
Arrangement of the Collection
Letter are in chronological order. Manuscripts are in alphabetical order by title. Miscellany is in alphabetical order by type.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Poetry; Markham, Edwin, 1852-1940.; Evening prayer.; Gray norns.; Sidney Lanier.; American poetry -- 20th century.; Poets -- American.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Manuscripts (document genre); Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Original collection gift of Sol Feinstone, John S. Mayfield.
"Outwitted" stanza gift of Martha Ash, 2015.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - to Elfreth, John, 7 Apr 1914 (Sc 148)
  - Desmond, A. E. (to John S. Mayfield), 14 Nov 1925 (Sc 148)
  - Markham, Anna Catherine (to John S. Mayfield), 15 Jun 1930 (Sc 148)
  - to Mayfield, John S., 15 Jun 1930 (Sc 148)
- Manuscripts
  - "Evening Prayer", autograph manuscript poem (Sc 148)
  - "The Gray Norns", 25 Nov 1917; autograph manuscript poem (Sc 148)
  - "Outwitted", single stanza, written in Markham's hand (Sc 148)
    Gift of Martha Ash, 2015. Formerly belonged to her stepmother, Amy Vanderbilt.
  - "Sidney Lanier", autograph manuscript essay (Sc 148)
- Miscellany
  - Broadside advertisement for Markham's California the Wonderful (Sc 148)
  - Cancelled check for $5, payable to Markham (Sc 148)
  - Clippings, 1924; 1932,; 1942 (Sc 148)